Register of the Estonian subject collection, 1935-2007
Hoover Institution Archives
Estonian Subject Collection,
1935-2007
XX810
15 manuscript boxes, 1 phonotape cassette. (6.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of Estonian history, and especially to the movement culminating in re-establishment of Estonian independence in 1991, and to subsequent Estonian politics and elections. Includes some material relating to the Baltic States collectively.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Estonia--History; Nationalism--Estonia; Estonia--Politics and government; Elections--Estonia; Estonia; Baltic States; Soviet Union; Phonotapes
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1935-1993. (Boxes 1-2)
  Reports, studies, memoranda, newletters, articles, pamphlets, printed matter and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SERIALS, 1940-1993. (Boxes 3-9)
  Magazines and newspapers published in Estonia. Arranged alphabetically by title.
- PHONOTAPE CASSETTE, 1992. (Cassette cabinet)
  One phonotape cassette recording of speeches of Estonian presidential candidates.
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1935-1993
  - Baltic Appeal to the United Nations. Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Estonia
    - Commerce. Gazel, Antoni, Foreign and Local Trade of the Baltic Countries, Torun, Poland, 1935. Published study (Folder 2)
    - Economic conditions. Ise Majandow Ettevote (IME), 1988. Report (Folder 3)
    - Elections
      - General (Folder 4)
      - 1990. U.S. Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, April 16, 1990. Report (Folder 5)
      - 1992 (Folder 6)
    - History
      - 20th centuryd. Roos, Aarand, Estonia: A Nation Unconquered, Baltimore. Mayland, 1985. Published study (Folder 7)
      - War of Independence, 1918-1920. Printed matter (Folder 8)
      - 1944-1991. Shtromas, Alexander, The Soviet Method of Conquest of the Baltic States Washington, D.C., 1986. Published study (Folder 9)
      - Independence movement, 1990 (Folder 10)
      - 1991-1992 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1992-1993 (Folder 13)
    - Law legislation (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - Official language, Law on, January 1989 (Folder 2)
    - Politics and government
      - Baltic Assembly, 1989 (Folder 3)
      - Eesti Kongress, March 1990 (Folder 4)
      - Rahvekongress, 1988 (Folder 5)
    - Religion
      - Christlich-Demokratische Union Estlands (Folder 6)
      - Estonian Evangelical Lutheran Church (Folder 7)
  - Estonian American National Council. "Erku Uudiste Ulevaade," 1991. Newsletters (Folder 8)
  - Estonians - United States
    - General (Folder 9-10)
    - Vaba Eesti Sona (New York), 1992. Newspaper clippings and selected issues (Folder 11)
  - Labor movement - Estonia. Mikhelson, Johannes, Estonian Labour in Chains, Lund, Sweden, 1955. Published study (Folder 12)
  - Nuclear free zones - Estonia (Folder 13)
  - Youth - Estonia. Pajur, Pia, Views of Estonian Young People, Tallinn, 1984. Published study (Folder 14)
- SERIALS, 1940-1993
  - Ari Paev (Tallinn)
    - 1989: No. 1; 1990: No. 3; 1992; Nos. 72-77 (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - 1992
      - Nos. 79-85 (Folder 2)
      - Nos. 86-93 (Folder 3)
      - Nos. 94-101 (Folder 4)
      - Nos. 102-112 (Folder 5)
      - Nos. 113-121 (Folder 6)
      - Nos. 122-127 (Folder 7)
  - Aspekt (Tallinn), 1990: No. 10 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Demokraatlik Mote (Tartu), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 2)
  - Eesti Aeg (Tallinn)
    - 1991
      - Nos. 1-3, 5, 6, 8-10 (Folder 3)
      - Nos. 12-15, 22-24, 26 (Folder 4)
    - 1992: Nos. 39, 40, 42-45 (Folder 5)
  - Eesti Ekspress (Tallinn)
    - 1989: No. 3; 1990: Nos. 6, 15; 1991: Nos. 25, 37; 1992: Nos. 44, 45 (Folder 6)
    - 1992
      - Nos. 46, 48 (Folder 7)
      - Nos. 49-51 (Folder 8)
  - Eesti Elu (Tallinn)
    - 1992: Nos. 2, 3, 16-19 (Folder 9)
    - 1992: Nos. 20, 21; 1993: No. 1 (Folder 10)
  - Eesti Kirik (Tallinn), 1990: Nos. 2, 3, 10; 1991: No. 21 (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Eesti Koda (Parnu), 1989: Nos. 1, 2; 1990: No. 3 (Folder 2)
  - Eesti Muinsuskaitse Seltsi Toimetisi (Tallinn), 1989: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 3)
  - Eesti Paevaleht (Tallinn)
    - 1992
      - Nos. 10-12, 14-17, 49-53, 55-58, 60-67 (Folder 4)
      - Nos. 68-92 (Folder 5)
    - 1992: Nos. 93-100; 1993: Nos. 1-6 (Folder 6)
    - 1993: Nos. 7-27 (Folder 7)
  - Eesti Rahvusliku Sotumatuse Partei Teataja (Tartu), 1989: No. 4 (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - Eesti Tuletorje (Tallinn), 1989: No. 1 (Folder 2)
  - Esmaspaev (Tallinn), 1990: No. 8; 1992: Nos. 40, 42-46 (Folder 3)
  - Estonian Life (Tallinn), 1992: Nos. 1-3 (Folder 4)
  - Hasachar "Koit" (Tallinn), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 5)
  - Homeland (Tallinn), 1988: Nos. 32-52; 1989: Nos. 1-51 (Folder 6)
  - Huudja Haal, 1990: No. 6; 1991: No. 10 (Folder 7)
  - Jutuleht (Tallinn), 1990: No. 4 (Folder 8)
  - Kaubaleht (Helsinki), 1990: Nos. 1-3; 1991: Nos. 1, 4 (Folder 9)
  - Kaubandus Toostuskoja (Tallinn), 1989: No. 2; 1990: No. 1 (Folder 10)
  - Kristlik Uhendus (Tallinn), 1989: No. 2; 1990: No. 3 (Folder 11)
  - Kungla Rahvas, 1990: Juuni (Folder 12)
  - Laane Elu (Neljapaev), 1989: No. 9 (Folder 13)
  - Liivimaa Kroonika (Tartu), 1990: No. 18 (Folder 14)
  - Marm (Tallinn), 1990: Nos. 3, 4 (Folder 15)
  - Meelejahutaja (Tallinn), 1989: No. 4; 1990: Nos. 1, 3, 5 (Folder 16)
  - Meie Meel (Tartu), 1991: No. 28 (Folder 17)
  - Memento (Tartu), 1989: No. 3; 1990: Nos. 1-12 (Folder 18)
  - Ohtuleht (Tallinn), 1992
    - Nos. 61-63, 92-96, 102-116 (Folder 19)
    - Nos. 117-151 (Box 7., Folder 1)
    - Nos. 158 -164, 181-186 (Folder 2)
    - Nos. 193-204 (Folder 3)
  - Oma Kodu (Tallinn), 1990: No. 4 (Folder 4)
  - Paevaleht (Tallinn), 1992
    - Nos. 238-262 (Folder 5)
    - Nos. 263-280 (Box 8., Folder 1)
  - Perekonnaleht Oma Kodu (Tallinn), 1990: Nos. 9, 11, 16 (Folder 2)
  - Pilk (Tallinn), 1989: No. 10; 1990: No. 2/3 (Folder 3)
  - Pisahand (Tallinn), 1989: September (Folder 4)
  - Postimees (Tallinn), 1992
    - Nos. 254-266 (Folder 5)
    - Nos. 267-279 (Folder 6)
    - Nos. 280-295 (Folder 7)
  - Rahvaleht (Tartu), 1990: Nos. 7, 12 (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - Revue Baltique (Tallinn), 1940: No. 2 (Folder 2)
  - Roheline (Tallinn), 1990: No. 16/18 (Folder 3)
  - Sirp (Tallinn), 1992: No. 46 (Folder 4)
  - Sodur (Tallinn), 1992: No. 1 (Folder 5)
  - Sona (Polva), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 6)
  - Sonumi Tooja (Tartu), 1990: Nos. 9, 11, 12 (Folder 7)
  - Sonumid (Tallinn), 1990: No. 1/2 (Folder 8)
  - Statistika Teataja (Tallinn), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 9)
  - Tartu Postipoiss (Tartu), 1989: Nos. 1-6, 8; 1990: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 10)
  - Teataja (Tallinn), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 11)
  - Teataja (Tartu), 1989: Nos. 2-6; 1990: No. 1 (Folder 12)
  - Themis (Tallinn), 1989: No. 3 (Folder 13)
  - Uliopilasleht (Tartu), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 14)
  - Vaba Eurooplane (Tallinn), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 15)
  - Vaba Maa (Tallinn)
    - 1989: Nos. 1-7, 11-29 (Folder 16)
    - 1990: Nos. 1-6 (Folder 17)
  - Videvik (Tallinn), 1990: No. 5/6 (Folder 18)
  - Voitleja (Tallinn), 1990: Nos. 4, 5 (Folder 19)
  - Voru Teataja (Tallinn), 1991: No. 35 (Folder 20)
- PHONOTAPE CASSETTE, 1992
  - Tape No. 1 - Speeches of Estonian presidential candidates, August 28 and September 5, 1992 (Oversize Cassette cabinet)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 10-15)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.